<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>

<sect1 id="ch-system-revisedchroot">
  <?dbhtml filename="revisedchroot.html"?>

  <title>Cleaning Up</title>

  <para>Finally, clean up some extra files left around from running tests:</para>

<screen><userinput>rm -rf /tmp/*</userinput></screen>

  <para>Now log out and reenter the chroot environment with an updated
  chroot command.  From now on, use this updated chroot command any time 
  you need to reenter the chroot environment after exiting:</para>

<screen role="nodump"><userinput>logout

chroot "$LFS" /usr/bin/env -i          \
    HOME=/root TERM="$TERM"            \
    PS1='(lfs chroot) \u:\w\$ '        \
    PATH=/bin:/usr/bin:/sbin:/usr/sbin \
    /bin/bash --login</userinput></screen>

  <para>The reason for this is that the programs in <filename
  class="directory">/tools</filename> are no longer needed.  For this reason
  you can delete the <filename class="directory">/tools</filename>
  directory if so desired.</para>

  <note>
    <para>Removing <filename class="directory">/tools</filename> will also
    remove the temporary copies of Tcl, Expect, and DejaGNU which were used
    for running the toolchain tests. If you need these programs later on,
    they will need to be recompiled and re-installed. The BLFS book has
    instructions for this (see <ulink url="&blfs-root;"/>).</para>
  </note>

  <para>If the virtual kernel file systems have been unmounted, either manually
  or through a reboot, ensure that the virtual kernel file systems are mounted
  when reentering the chroot. This process was explained in <xref
  linkend="ch-system-bindmount"/> and <xref
  linkend="ch-system-kernfsmount"/>.</para>

  <para>There were several static libraries that were not suppressed earlier
  in the chapter in order to satisfy the regression tests in several packages. These 
  libraries are from binutils, bzip2, e2fsprogs, flex, libtool, and zlib.  If desired,
  remove them now:</para>

<screen><userinput>rm -f /usr/lib/lib{bfd,opcodes}.a
rm -f /usr/lib/libbz2.a
rm -f /usr/lib/lib{com_err,e2p,ext2fs,ss}.a
rm -f /usr/lib/libltdl.a
rm -f /usr/lib/libfl.a
rm -f /usr/lib/libz.a</userinput></screen>

  <para>There are also several files installed in the /usr/lib and /usr/libexec
  directories with a file name extention of .la. These are "libtool archive"
  files and generally unneeded on a linux system. None of these are necessary
  at this point. To remove them, run:</para>

<screen><userinput>find /usr/lib /usr/libexec -name \*.la -delete</userinput></screen>

   <para>For more information about libtool archive files, see the <ulink
   url="&blfs-book;/introduction/la-files.html">BLFS section "About Libtool
   Archive (.la) files"</ulink>.</para>

</sect1>
