<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>

<sect1 id="space-creatingpartition">
  <?dbhtml filename="creatingpartition.html"?>

  <title>Creating a New Partition</title>

  <para>Like most other operating systems, LFS is usually installed on a
  dedicated partition. The recommended approach to building an LFS system
  is to use an available empty partition or, if you have enough unpartitioned
  space, to create one.</para>

<!--

  <para>It is possible to install an LFS system (in fact even multiple LFS
  systems) on a partition already occupied by another
  operating system and the different systems will co-exist peacefully. The
  document <ulink url="&hints-root;lfs_next_to_existing_systems.txt"/>
  contains notes on how to implement this. This document was last updated
  in 2004. It has not been updated since and it has not been tested with
  recent versions of this LFS book. The document is more than likely not
  usable as-is and you will need to account for changes made to the LFS
  procedures since it was written. This is only recommended for expert LFS
  users.</para>

-->

  <para>A minimal system requires a partition of around 4 gigabytes (GB).
  This is enough to store all the source tarballs and compile the packages.
  However, if the LFS system is intended to be the primary Linux system,
  additional software will probably be installed which will require additional
  space. A 10 GB partition is a reasonable size to provide for growth.  The LFS
  system itself will not take up this much room.  A large portion of this
  requirement is to provide sufficient free temporary storage. Compiling
  packages can require a lot of disk space which will be reclaimed after the
  package is installed.</para>

  <para>Because there is not always enough Random Access Memory (RAM) available
  for compilation processes, it is a good idea to use a small disk partition as
  <systemitem class="filesystem">swap</systemitem> space. This is used by the
  kernel to store seldom-used data and leave more memory available for active
  processes. The <systemitem class="filesystem">swap</systemitem> partition for
  an LFS system can be the same as the one used by the host system, in which
  case it is not necessary to create another one.</para>

  <para>Start a disk partitioning program such as <command>cfdisk</command>
  or <command>fdisk</command> with a command line option naming the hard
  disk on which the new partition will be created&mdash;for example
  <filename class="devicefile">/dev/sda</filename> for the primary Integrated
  Drive Electronics (IDE) disk. Create a Linux native partition and a
  <systemitem class="filesystem">swap</systemitem> partition, if needed. Please
  refer to <filename>cfdisk(8)</filename> or <filename>fdisk(8)</filename> if
  you do not yet know how to use the programs.</para>

  <note><para>For experienced users, other partitioning schemes are possible.
  The new LFS system can be on a software <ulink
  url="&blfs-book;postlfs/raid.html">RAID</ulink> array or an <ulink
  url="&blfs-book;postlfs/aboutlvm.html">LVM</ulink> logical volume.
  However, some of these options require an <ulink
  url="&blfs-book;postlfs/initramfs.html">initramfs</ulink>, which is
  an advanced topic.  These partitioning methodologies are not recommended for
  first time LFS users.</para></note>

  <para>Remember the designation of the new partition (e.g., <filename
  class="devicefile">sda5</filename>). This book will refer to this as
  the LFS partition. Also remember the designation of the <systemitem
  class="filesystem">swap</systemitem> partition. These names will be
  needed later for the <filename>/etc/fstab</filename> file.</para>

  <sect2>
  <title>Other Partition Issues</title>

  <para>Requests for advice on system partitioning are often posted on the LFS mailing
  lists.  This is a highly subjective topic.  The default for most distributions
  is to use the entire drive with the exception of one small swap partition.  This
  is not optimal for LFS for several reasons.  It reduces flexibility, makes
  sharing of data across multiple distributions or LFS builds more difficult, makes
  backups more time consuming, and can waste disk space through inefficient
  allocation of file system structures.</para>

    <sect3>
    <title>The Root Partition</title>

    <para>A root LFS partition (not to be confused with the
    <filename class="directory">/root</filename> directory) of
    ten gigabytes is a good compromise for most systems.  It provides enough
    space to build LFS and most of BLFS, but is small enough so that multiple
    partitions can be easily created for experimentation.</para> </sect3>

    <sect3>
    <title>The Swap Partition</title>

    <para>Most distributions automatically create a swap partition.  Generally
    the recommended size of the swap partition is about twice the amount of
    physical RAM, however this is rarely needed.  If disk space is limited,
    hold the swap partition to two gigabytes and monitor the amount of disk
    swapping.</para>

    <para>Swapping is never good.  Generally you can tell if a system is
    swapping by just listening to disk activity and observing how the system
    reacts to commands.  The first reaction to swapping should be to check for
    an unreasonable command such as trying to edit a five gigabyte file.  If
    swapping becomes a normal occurrence, the best solution is to purchase more
    RAM for your system.</para> </sect3>

    <sect3>
    <title>Convenience Partitions</title>

    <para>There are several other partitions that are not required, but should
    be considered when designing a disk layout.  The following list
    is not comprehensive, but is meant as a guide.</para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem><para>/boot &ndash; Highly recommended.  Use this partition to
      store kernels and other booting information.  To minimize potential boot
      problems with larger disks, make this the first physical partition on
      your first disk drive.  A partition size of 100 megabytes is quite
      adequate.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>/home &ndash; Highly recommended.  Share your home
      directory and user customization across multiple distributions or LFS
      builds.  The size is generally fairly large and depends on available disk
      space.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>/usr &ndash; A separate /usr partition is generally used
      if providing a server for a thin client or diskless workstation.  It is
      normally not needed for LFS.  A size of five gigabytes will handle most
      installations.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>/opt &ndash; This directory is most useful for
      BLFS where multiple installations of large packages like Gnome or KDE can
      be installed without embedding the files in the /usr hierarchy.  If
      used, 5 to 10 gigabytes is generally adequate.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para>/tmp &ndash; A separate /tmp directory is rare, but
      useful if configuring a thin client.  This partition, if used, will
      usually not need to exceed a couple of gigabytes.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>/usr/src &ndash; This partition is very
      useful for providing a location to store BLFS source files and
      share them across LFS builds.  It can also be used as a location
      for building BLFS packages.  A reasonably large partition of 30-50
      gigabytes allows plenty of room.</para></listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Any separate partition that you want automatically mounted upon boot
    needs to be specified in the <filename>/etc/fstab</filename>.  Details
    about how to specify partitions will be discussed in <xref
    linkend="ch-bootable-fstab"/>.  </para>

    </sect3>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
