<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>

<sect1 id="prepare-abouttestsuites">
  <?dbhtml filename="abouttestsuites.html"?>

  <title>About the Test Suites</title>

  <para>Most packages provide a test suite. Running the test suite for a
  newly built package is a good idea because it can provide a <quote>sanity
  check</quote> indicating that everything compiled correctly. A test suite
  that passes its set of checks usually proves that the package is
  functioning as the developer intended. It does not, however, guarantee
  that the package is totally bug free.</para>

  <para>Some test suites are more important than others. For example,
  the test suites for the core toolchain packages&mdash;GCC, Binutils, and
  Glibc&mdash;are of the utmost importance due to their central role in a
  properly functioning system. The test suites for GCC and Glibc can
  take a very long time to complete, especially on slower hardware, but
  are strongly recommended.</para>

  <note>
    <para>Experience has shown that there is little to be gained from running
    the test suites in <xref linkend="chapter-temporary-tools"/>. There can be
    no escaping the fact that the host system always exerts some influence on
    the tests in that chapter, often causing inexplicable failures. Because
    the tools built in <xref linkend="chapter-temporary-tools"/> are temporary
    and eventually discarded, we do not recommend running the test suites in
    <xref linkend="chapter-temporary-tools"/> for the average reader. The
    instructions for running those test suites are provided for the benefit of
    testers and developers, but they are strictly optional.</para>
  </note>

  <para>A common issue with running the test suites for Binutils and GCC
  is running out of pseudo terminals (PTYs). This can result in a high
  number of failing tests. This may happen for several reasons, but the
  most likely cause is that the host system does not have the
  <systemitem class="filesystem">devpts</systemitem> file system set up
  correctly. This issue is discussed in greater detail at
  <ulink url="&lfs-root;lfs/faq.html#no-ptys"/>.</para>

  <para>Sometimes package test suites will fail, but for reasons which the
  developers are aware of and have deemed non-critical. Consult the logs located
  at <ulink url="&test-results;"/> to verify whether or not these failures are
  expected. This site is valid for all tests throughout this book.</para>

</sect1>
