<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>

<sect1 id="pre-typography">
  <?dbhtml filename="typography.html"?>

  <title>Typography</title>

  <para>To make things easier to follow, there are a few typographical
  conventions used throughout this book. This section contains some
  examples of the typographical format found throughout Linux From
  Scratch.</para>

<screen role="nodump"><userinput>./configure --prefix=/usr</userinput></screen>

  <para>This form of text is designed to be typed exactly as seen unless
  otherwise noted in the surrounding text. It is also used in the explanation
  sections to identify which of the commands is being referenced.</para>

  <para>In some cases, a logical line is extended to two or more physical lines
  with a backslash at the end of the line.</para>

<screen role="nodump"><userinput>CC="gcc -B/usr/bin/" ../binutils-2.18/configure \
  --prefix=/tools --disable-nls --disable-werror</userinput></screen>

  <para>Note that the backslash must be followed by an immediate return.  Other
  whitespace characters like spaces or tab characters will create incorrect
  results.</para>

<screen><computeroutput>install-info: unknown option '--dir-file=/mnt/lfs/usr/info/dir'</computeroutput></screen>

  <para>This form of text (fixed-width text) shows screen output, usually as
  the result of commands issued.  This format is also used to show filenames,
  such as <filename>/etc/ld.so.conf</filename>.</para>

  <para><emphasis>Emphasis</emphasis></para>

  <para>This form of text is used for several purposes in the book. Its main
  purpose is to emphasize important points or items.</para>

  <para><ulink url="&lfs-root;"/></para>

  <para>This format is used for hyperlinks both within the LFS community and to
  external pages. It includes HOWTOs, download locations, and websites.</para>

<screen role="nodump"><userinput>cat &gt; $LFS/etc/group &lt;&lt; "EOF"
<literal>root:x:0:
bin:x:1:
......</literal>
EOF</userinput></screen>

  <para>This format is used when creating configuration files. The first command
  tells the system to create the file <filename>$LFS/etc/group</filename> from
  whatever is typed on the following lines until the sequence End Of File (EOF)
  is encountered. Therefore, this entire section is generally typed as
  seen.</para>

  <para><replaceable>&lt;REPLACED TEXT&gt;</replaceable></para>

  <para>This format is used to encapsulate text that is not to be typed
  as seen or for copy-and-paste operations.</para>

  <para><replaceable>[OPTIONAL TEXT]</replaceable></para>

  <para>This format is used to encapsulate text that is optional.</para>

  <para><filename>passwd(5)</filename></para>

  <para>This format is used to refer to a specific manual (man) page. The number inside parentheses
  indicates a specific section inside the manuals. For example,
  <command>passwd</command> has two man pages. Per LFS installation instructions,
  those two man pages will be located at
  <filename>/usr/share/man/man1/passwd.1</filename> and
  <filename>/usr/share/man/man5/passwd.5</filename>. When the book uses <filename>passwd(5)</filename> it is
  specifically referring to <filename>/usr/share/man/man5/passwd.5</filename>.
  <command>man passwd</command> will print the first man page it finds that
  matches <quote>passwd</quote>, which will be
  <filename>/usr/share/man/man1/passwd.1</filename>. For this example, you will
  need to run <command>man 5 passwd</command> in order to read the specific page
  being referred to. It should be noted that most man pages do not have duplicate
  page names in different sections. Therefore, <command>man <replaceable>&lt;program
  name&gt;</replaceable></command> is generally sufficient.</para>

</sect1>

