<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../general.ent">
  <!ENTITY site               SYSTEM "../appendices/rc.site.script">
  %general-entities;
]>

<sect1 id="ch-scripts-site">
  <?dbhtml filename="site.html"?>

  <title>The rc.site File</title>

  <indexterm zone="ch-scripts-site">
    <primary sortas="a-rc.site">rc.site</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>The optional <filename>/etc/sysconfig/rc.site</filename> file contains
  settings that are automatically set for each SystemV boot script.  It can
  alternatively set the values specified in the <filename>hostname</filename>,
  <filename>console</filename>, and <filename>clock</filename> files in the
  <filename class='directory'>/etc/sysconfig/</filename> directory.  If the
  associated variables are present in both these separate files and
  <filename>rc.site</filename>, the values in the script specific files have
  precedence. </para>

  <para><filename>rc.site</filename> also contains parameters that can
  customize other aspects of the boot process.  Setting the IPROMPT variable
  will enable selective running of bootscripts.  Other options are described
  in the file comments.  The default version of the file is as follows:</para>

  <!-- Use role to fix a pdf generation problem -->
  <screen role="auto">&site;</screen>

  <sect2>
    <title>Customizing the Boot and Shutdown Scripts</title>

    <para>The LFS boot scripts boot and shut down a system in a fairly
    efficient manner, but there are a few tweaks that you can make in the
    rc.site file to improve speed even more and to adjust messages according
    to your preferences. To do this, adjust the settings in
    the <filename>/etc/sysconfig/rc.site</filename> file above.</para>

    <itemizedlist>

    <listitem><para>During the boot script <filename>udev</filename>, there is
    a call to <command>udev settle</command> that requires some time to
    complete. This time may or may not be required depending on devices present
    in the system.  If you only have simple partitions and a single ethernet
    card, the boot process will probably not need to wait for this command.  To
    skip it, set the variable OMIT_UDEV_SETTLE=y.</para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>The boot script <filename>udev_retry</filename> also runs
    <command>udev settle</command> by default.  This command is only needed by
    default if the <filename class='directory'>/var</filename> directory is
    separately mounted.  This is because the clock needs the file
    <filename>/var/lib/hwclock/adjtime</filename>.  Other customizations may
    also need to wait for udev to complete, but in many installations it is not
    needed.  Skip the command by setting the variable OMIT_UDEV_RETRY_SETTLE=y.
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>By default, the file system checks are silent.  This can
    appear to be a delay during the bootup process.  To turn on the
    <command>fsck</command> output, set the variable VERBOSE_FSCK=y.
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>When rebooting, you may want to skip the filesystem check,
    <command>fsck</command>, completely.  To do this, either create the file
    <filename>/fastboot</filename> or reboot the system with the command
    <command>/sbin/shutdown -f -r now</command>.  On the other hand, you can
    force all file systems to be checked by creating
    <filename>/forcefsck</filename> or running <command>shutdown</command> with
    the <parameter>-F</parameter> parameter instead of <parameter>-f</parameter>.
    </para>

    <para>Setting the variable FASTBOOT=y will disable <command>fsck</command>
    during the boot process until it is removed.  This is not recommended
    on a permanent basis.</para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>Normally, all files in the <filename
    class='directory'>/tmp</filename> directory are deleted at boot time.
    Depending on the number of files or directories present, this can cause a
    noticeable delay in the boot process.  To skip removing these files set the
    variable SKIPTMPCLEAN=y.</para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>During shutdown, the <command>init</command> program sends
    a TERM signal to each program it has started (e.g. agetty), waits for a set
    time (default 3 seconds), and sends each process a KILL signal and waits
    again.  This process is repeated in the <command>sendsignals</command>
    script for any processes that are not shut down by their own scripts.  The
    delay for <command>init</command> can be set by passing a parameter.  For
    example to remove the delay in <command>init</command>, pass the -t0
    parameter when shutting down or rebooting (e.g.  <command>/sbin/shutdown
    -t0 -r now</command>).  The delay for the  <command>sendsignals</command>
    script can be skipped by setting the parameter
    KILLDELAY=0.</para></listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

  </sect2>

</sect1>

